Good morning. Our דף daf. *daf* today is דף daf ע"ו *daf
ayin vav*, 76. We pick up on the bottom of ע"ה עמוד
ב׳ *ayin hey amud bet* right after the גמרא gemara *Gemara*—right after
the משנה Mishnah *mishnah* starting at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. The משנה
mishnah *mishnah* says that if an
אשם Asham *asham*, which tends to be male, gets mixed up with
another sacrifice, a שלמים Shelamim. *shlamim*, which could be male or female—basically
an אשם Asham *asham* is male, a חטאת chatas *chatas* is female,
an עולה olah? *olah* is male, and a שלמים Shelamim *shlamim* can
be either—so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* before, yesterday, dealt with what scenarios
could things get mixed up, because if certain מינים *minim* is only
male and certain is only female, then you're never going to get
them confused. But anyway, anything can get mixed up with a שלמים
shelamim *shlamim* because a שלמים shelamim. *shlamim* is male or female. So
an אשם asham *asham* gets mixed up with a שלמים shelamim *shlamim*.
So, fine, play it safe. שחט *Shecht* it in the north and
have the כהנים kohanim *kohanim*, male כהנים kohanim *kohanim* eat it as
an אשם asham. *asham*. I mean שחט *shecht* both of them in
the north, so that whichever one is an אשם asham, *asham* you're
eating correctly, and whichever one is a שלמים shelamim? *shlamim*, there's nothing
wrong with שחט *shechting* a שלמים shelamim. *shlamim* in the north and
with having male כהנים kohanim. *kohanim* eat it. Okay, and that's basically
the position of רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon *Rabbi Shimon*. And the blood,
they're both below anyway, because only a חטאת chatas *chatas* is up.
And the blood is in the same place; everything other than a
חטאת chatas *chatas*, the blood is in the same place. Comes along
the חכמים *Chachamim* and the חכמים *Chachamim* say no, that that's not
going to work because you're limiting the people and the time in
which the שלמים shelamim *shlamim* can be eaten. It can only be
eaten by male כהנים kohanim. *kohanim*; more significantly, it can only be
eaten for one day, not for two days, and
therefore, you're raising the likelihood that some of the meat will become
נותר *nosar* and have to be burned. But isn't it considered—well, right.
That's called אין מביאים קדשים לבית הפסול kodshim leveis hapusul *ain mevi'im
kodshim l'bet hapsul*. You don't bring sacrifices into the house of invalidity,
meaning you don't sort of put them in a context in which
it's more likely they'll become invalid. So Michael says correctly, so what
are you supposed to do? So what you're supposed to do is
you wait until they get a blemish and then
you basically redeem it and you say, whichever one of these animals
is an אשם asham *asham*, its value goes on this money, and
use this money to buy an אשם asham, *asham*, and whichever one
is a שלמים shelamim *shlamim*, its value goes on this money, and
use this money to buy a שלמים shelamim *shlamim*, and then you
know which is which. But okay, it takes time and you have
to wait for them to get a blemish, etc. So that's why
the obvious response to רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* is like,
well—רבי שמעון's Rebbe Shimon *Rabbi Shimon's* obvious response to the חכמים *Chachamim*
who've got this problem is, well, do you have a better
solution? And the answer is, well, yeah, we do have a better
solution. But presumably, if you didn't have a better solution, what else
are you supposed to do, better do this than to just have
them go to waste. All right, so that's presumably that is the
point that רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon *Rabbi Shimon*—it's a question about whether
to do this or not when there's a different possible solution. So
let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. תני תנא קמיה
דרב *Tanni tanna kamei d'rav*. So the תנא *tanna* taught in front
of רב *Rav*. שביעית Shviis *Shvi'is*, if you have שביעית Shviis *shvi'is*
money, אין לוקחים בדמיה תרומה truma. *ain lokchim b'dameha trumah*. You don't
buy תרומה truma? *trumah* with your שביעית Shviis *shvi'is* money. Why? Because
things you buy with שביעית Shviis, *shvi'is* money, like fruit you sold
and then it gets קדושת שביעית shvi'is. *kdushas shvi'is*, what you buy
with it, if you buy fruit—anything you have that has קדושת שביעית
shvi'is *kdushas shvi'is*, at a certain point in the year when the
fruit is no longer available for the animals out in the field,
you have to destroy—you're not allowed to keep—you have to destroy the
food that you have at home, the
שביעית *shvi'is* produce. That's called שעת הביעור *shas habiyur*. And if you
bought food with
the money that had קדושת שביעית *kdushas shvi'is*, the same הלכה halacha,
*halacha* would apply. And how did this happen exactly? You're not supposed
to sell your fruit. No, you're allowed to sell if it's not
commercial or whatever. Okay, there are circumstances in which you can sell
שביעית *shvi'is* and the money transfers. Whether you were supposed to or
not, it doesn't matter. You have money that has קדושת שביעית *kdushas
shvi'is*. So don't use that money to buy תרומה truma *trumah*. Why?
Because now you're going to make the תרומה truma *trumah* have קדושת
שביעית *kdushas shvi'is* and you might have to destroy the תרומה truma
*trumah* if you don't eat it in time. So that's an example
of מביאים קדשים kodshim לבית הפסול *mevi'im kodshim l'bet hapsul*. Now it
is interesting because this is not קדשים kodshim? *kodshim*, it's not קרבנות
Korbanos *korbanot*. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is willing to assume that
the same would be true by grain that has קדושה Kedusha *kdushah*,
if it's תרומה truma *trumah*, if it's מעשר שני ma'aser sheni *maiser
sheini* whatever we'll see, that this question about can you put it
in a context where you might have to destroy it earlier will
come up. Okay, so the ברייתא *braita* says, אין לוקחים בדמיה תרומה
truma מפני שממעטין אכילתה *ain lokchim b'dameha trumah mipnei shemima'atin achilasah*. Because
you limit the time of eating. Okay, that's a reasonable position. אין
מביאים קדשים kodshim לבית הפסול *ain mevi'im kodshim l'bet hapsul*. אמרו רבנן
קמיה דרבא *Amru rabbanan kamei d'Rava*—so the Rabbis said this in front
of רבא Rava. *Rava* or רבה Raba *Rabbah*. After they heard this
ברייתא *braita*, they repeated it and they said, הא דלא כרבי שמעון
*hadda lo k'Rabbi Shimon*. Presumably the author of that ברייתא *braita* is
not like רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon *Rabbi Shimon*, because רבי שמעון Rebbe
Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* of our משנה mishnah *mishnah* doesn't have a problem
with putting it in a context where it might get destroyed earlier.
דאי רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon. הא אמר מביאים קדשים kodshim. לבית הפסול
*d'ei Rabbi Shimon ha amar mevi'im kodshim l'bet hapsul*. רבי שמעון Rebbe
Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* says you're allowed to do that and put things
in a context where they might have to get destroyed earlier, so
you should be allowed to buy תרומה truma. *trumah* with your שמיטה
shmita *shmitah* money. אמר להו *Amar lehu*—so רבא Rava *Rava* said back
to them, אפילו תימא רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon. *afilu teima Rabbi Shimon*.
No, no, no, no. Even רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* of
our משנה mishnah *mishnah* would agree not to do that with your
שביעית *shvi'is* money. Why? הני מילי דיעבד D'ieved. *hani mili d'i'avad*. I
like this because דיעבד D'ieved *d'i'avad* is written out fully. דיעבד D'ieved
*d'i'avad*... It is really a contraction of two words, דאי עבד, if
it was already done. Okay, when did רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon in
our משנה Mishna say that you can do it? Because you have
like already the stuff is already mixed up and you don't have
a choice. So for him he just felt that was the best
solution to a problem. If you've got a problem, he feels that
this is a possible solution to it, even if it means you
might have to destroy, you know, the קרבן korban as only has
one day rather than two days. But לכתחילה לא. lechatchila lo. But
if you just have שמיטה shmita money, he's not going to let
you use that שמיטה money to buy תרומה. truma He's not going
to let you לכתחילה lechatchila get something in a bad status like
that that you might have to destroy it, okay? If it's already
in a problematic status, he might say he will say that this
is a legitimate solution. But why would he לכתחילה lechatchila let you
use that money to buy תרומה? truma. Very reasonable position. Okay. So
now we're going to explore that for a lot of today's דף.
daf Will רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon allow you to do this לכתחילה?
lechatchila? Is he completely unconcerned with this idea? He'll just say I
trust you to be responsible and I'm completely unconcerned or is he
saying I'll allow it when the situation warrants. Okay. So the גמרא
Gemara says ולכתחילה לא? v'lechatchila lo? Would he really not allow this
לכתחילה? lechatchila? איתיבי, eiseivi, I'll ask you on this.
איתיבי אביי, eiseivi Abaye, Abaye challenges. So he's challenging רבא. Rava, רבא
Rava is the one who says he would not say it לכתחילה.
lechatchila. אביי, Abaye, a student of רבא, Rava. is now going to
challenge where it's going to look like from various משניות mishnayos or
whatever that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon will allow it לכתחילה. lechatchila. This
would have been perfect if it was Rab because that would be...
I understand. Okay. וכולן רשאין, v'chulan resha'in, so a later משנה Mishna
teaches all of them, all the various sacrifices. וכולן, v'chulan, excuse me,
רשאין הכהנים לשנות אכילתן. resha'in hakohanim l'shanos achilatan. The כהנים kohanim can
do, you know, eat them anyway they want. Okay. Remember the משנה
Mishna that we set up ונאכלים לכל מאכל, v'ne'echalin l'chol ma'achal, can
be eaten in any way. So here the משנה Mishna, spells this
out. All these sacrifices can be eaten by the כהנים kohanim however
they want. לאוכלן צלויין
שלוקין מבושלין, l'ochlan tzloyim shelukim mevushalim, roasted, double boiled, baked, cooked.
That's like my nephew's four questions, צליש שלוקים מבושל. tzlish shelukim mevushal.
Right, exactly. ולתת לתוכן תבלי חולין, v'latet l'tochan tavlei chulin, and they
can put in any spices that they want. By the way, spices
does not just mean like ground up peppercorn, it also actually means
like onions and garlic and so on, okay. תבלי חולין tavlei chulin
ותבלי תרומה, v'tavlei truma, and even תרומה truma spices. They can throw
in some תרומה truma, onions into it. Okay. But this is your,
this is your קרבן? korban? No, but you're cooking it in like
your pot? Like... Yeah, I don't, we're not paying attention to the
pot right now.
דברי רבי שמעון. divrei Rebbe Shimon. That's what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
says. Now, why is this a חידוש? chiddush? Because you have your
תרומה truma onion, you throw it in your, you know, חטאת chatas
pot, your חטאת chatas, with your, you know, your חטאת chatas stew.
Now this תרומה truma onion you're only going to be able to
eat for one day, right? You got it? So how come רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon allows you לכתחילה lechatchila to throw your תרומה truma.
onion into your חטאת chatas stew? That's מביא קדשים לבית הפסול. meivi
kodshim l'veis hapesul. The קדשים kodshim. here is the תרומה. Truma Okay.
The תרומה Truma, now you're limiting the time of eating. So you
see that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon allows it even לכתחילה. lechatchila. Okay.
That's a pretty good proof. So אמר ליה, amar lei, so רבא
Rava. said back to him, הניח לתרומת תבלין דרבנן. hanach l'trumas tavlin
derabbanan. Don't bother me about תבלין, tavlin, about, you know, garlic and
onions. That's all vegetables, vegetables is only
rabbinic תרומה. Truma You said Ishmael. I know, but the side correct
says it correctly, it's רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon Yeah, it would only
make sense if it's רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon because we're asking within
רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon Okay. Don't bother me about that. When it's
a
rabbinic type of a thing, he'll allow you to put it in
that circumstance. But if it's biblical, he won't let you do it
if there's another option. He won't let you do it לכתחילה. lechatchila.
Not if there's another option, excuse me, but he wouldn't let you
do it לכתחילה. lechatchila. He'll only let you do it when you've
got to solve a problem. Okay. איתיבי. eiseivi. All right, let me
challenge this assertion again. I'm going to try again to prove that
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon will allow it
לכתחילה. lechatchila. אין לוקחין תרומה בכסף מעשר מפני שממעט באכילתה. ein lokchin
truma b'kesef ma'aser mipnei shemema'et b'achilatah. You don't buy תרומה Truma with
מעשר ma'aser money, so מעשר ma'aser money means מעשר שני ma'aser sheni
money, because you limit its time of being eaten. So there's a
fascinating debate here between רש"י Rashi and תוספות. Tosafos. What are you
limiting?
רש"י Rashi says you're limiting the ability to eat the תרומה, Truma
okay, because we were just talking about תרומה Truma a minute ago,
okay. Why? Because what do you mean?
תרומה Truma can be eaten anyway and מעשר שני ma'aser sheni can
only be eaten in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So that's a little funny. Normally
we talk about limiting the time. Here it's limiting the circumstances. But
you could understand limiting the circumstances could also lead to problems. Although
it's not exactly the same because I could just, I mean, I
guess things rot, but you know, if it's just a question of
location, I could just wait until next time I'm going to ירושלים.
Yerushalayim. Anyway, רש"י Rashi says what you're doing is you're limiting the
תרומה. Truma, תוספות Tosafos says no, it's the opposite. You're limiting the
מעשר ma'aser because you're taking מעשר שני ma'aser sheni that could be
eaten by anybody and now you're making it that it can only
be eaten by כהנים. kohanim So according to either, now מעשר שני
ma'aser sheni is now where of קדשים? Now מעשר ma'aser שני is
in the קדשים category.
No one has a problem with
חולין *chullin* though? What? Correct. Okay. So anyway, but also, but in
neither of the cases are you limiting the time, okay? So either
way it's a חידוש chiddush *chiddush* that מביאים קדשים לבית הפסול *mevi'im
kodshim l'veit hap'sul* here is not a question about time, alright? I
mean although you could say that like since you can only do
it in ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, who's going to be in ירושלים *Yerushalayim* the
whole time? Right? In other words like I can eat something
everywhere and now I can only eat something like תרומה Truma *terumah*
I could eat anywhere outside of ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. So but now this
I can only eat in ירושלים *Yerushalayim* and especially if you're not
from ירושלים *Yerushalayim* you have to go up there for
it. I understand. So all these things increase the likelihood that you
might have to you might wind up rotting or throwing it out
and so on. But the point is that it's worth noting though
that we moved from a case where there was clearly like a
clock running out, okay, whether the clock was a שביעית *Shvi'is* clock
or a or a one day חטאת *Chatas* clock to a case
about where it's a question about fewer people or fewer locations. Okay,
anyway, one way or another you can't do this because it's going
to to limit its ability to be eaten. ורבי שמעון
מתיר *v'Rabbi Shimon mattir* and Rabbi Shimon allows it. So here you
have Rabbi Shimon allowing it לכתחילה L'chatchila *l'chatchilah*, okay,
and presumably here we're dealing with דאורייתא D'oraysa. *d'Oraisa*, nobody is limiting
this to a case where the thing that you're that's a problem
here whether the problem is the מעשר *ma'aser* or the תרומה Truma
*terumah* is only a דרבנן derabanan *d'Rabbanan*. So here presumably it's a
דאורייתא *d'Oraisa* thing that you're limiting its ability to be eaten and
Rabbi Shimon allows it לכתחילה L'chatchila. *l'chatchilah*. So that is pretty much
a slam dunk good proof that Rabbi Shimon allows it לכתחילה L'chatchila
*l'chatchilah*. But interestingly now the rest of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s discussion
is going to sort of bracket the point that you just proved
your
point and say wait a minute there's a lot of other משניות
*Mishnayos* that we could have quoted where it seems evident that Rabbi
Shimon allows this לכתחילה L'chatchila *l'chatchilah*. So even though you've brought a
משנה Mishna *Mishnah* that proved it, so now we're going to get
into a whole discussion of why didn't you bring this משנה Mishna.
*Mishnah*, why didn't you bring this משנה mishna. *Mishnah*? There's a lot
of other משניות *Mishnayos* that seem to make this point okay that
Rabbi Shimon allows it לכתחילה L'chatchila *l'chatchilah*. So let's take a look.
Okay, כי אתא לקמיה דרב יוסף *ki ata l'kamei d'Rav Yosef*, now
when רב יוסף Rav Yosef, *Rav Yosef* so אביי Abaye *Abaye* challenged
רבה *Rabbah* and proved רבה *Rabbah* said Rabbi Shimon doesn't allow it
לכתחילה L'chatchila? *l'chatchilah*, okay, רב יוסף Rav Yosef *Rav Yosef* and רבה
*Rabbah* are contemporaries. אביי Abaye *Abaye* is the next generation. So רבה
*Rabbah* said Rabbi Shimon doesn't allow it לכתחילה L'chatchila *l'chatchilah*, אביי Abaye
*Abaye* proved that he did from this last משנה Mishnah: *Mishnah* we
just quoted and now אביי Abaye *Abaye* is coming to רב יוסף
Rav Yosef *Rav Yosef* and telling him over here's what רבה *Rabbah*
said, here's how I
argued that it should be that Rabbi Shimon does allow it לכתחילה
L'chatchila. *l'chatchilah*. So כי אתא לקמיה דרב יוסף אמר ליה *ki ata
l'kamei d'Rav Yosef amar lei*, רב יוסף Rav Yosef, *Rav Yosef* said
to אביי *Abaye*, אמאי לא תספיה מהא *amai lo tosfei meihah*? Why
didn't you challenge רבה *Rabbah* from this other משנה *Mishnah*? We've got
other משניות *Mishnayos* that make it clear that Rabbi Shimon allows it
לכתחילה lechatchila, *l'chatchilah*. What other משנה *Mishnah*? A משנה *Mishnah* in שביעית
*Shvi'is*. אין מבשלין ירק של שביעית בשמן של תרומה *ein m'vashlin yerek
shel Shvi'is b'shemen shel terumah*. You don't go ahead and take a
שביעית *Shvi'is* vegetable and cook it in תרומה *terumah* oil, alright? שלא
יביאו קדשים לבית הפסול *shelo yavi'u kodshim l'veit hap'sul*. There exactly by
the way this is important because this is because here's the phrase,
the same phrase we had in our משנה *Mishnah*. You don't bring
and here קדשים *kodshim* is explicitly being used in a non קרבן
korban. *korban* context. You don't bring the קדשים *kodshim* to the house
of invalidity. Which is the קדשים *kodshim* you're bringing to the house
of invalidity? Okay, the תרומה *terumah* here is now again being limited
in the time that it can be eaten because you're cooking it
with a שביעית *Shvi'is* product. So now you are limiting the ability
of the תרומה *terumah* to be eaten. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon מתיר
*Rabbi Shimon mattir*, again Rabbi Shimon allows it לכתחילה lechatchila *l'chatchilah*. Okay.
אמר ליה אביי *amar lei Abaye*, so אביי *Abaye* says, ולאו משום
הא דתבלין *v'lav mishum meihah d'tavlin*? There was a reason I didn't
quote that משנה *Mishnah* because I had already asked him from this
case of תבלין *tavlin* of putting like the onions and the garlic
in the pot. ואמר ליה הנך לתרומת תבלין דרבנן *v'amar lei hanach
l'trumas tavlin d'Rabbanan*. And he said don't bother me with something that's
only rabbinic. I'm not rabbinic fine Rabbi Shimon would allow it. So
הכא נמי תרומת ירק דרבנן *hacha nami trumas yerek d'Rabbanan*. So I
didn't bother asking him from the case about the vegetable and the
oil because he would have said to me yeah that's also rabbinic,
the vegetable oil. Well but okay but the vegetable is only rabbinically
תרומה *terumah*. So that's why he would have just dismissed it and
therefore I didn't bother I didn't bother asking that. Okay. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אי הכי Hachi איפכא מיבעי ליה למיתני *ihachi
ipcha mibei lei l'misnei*. So רב יוסף Rav Yosef *Rav Yosef* said
back to אביי *Abaye* no I'm sorry אביי *Abaye* this actually was
a good proof because here what are you limiting the time of
eating? Remember you've got a תרומה *terumah* carrot and... No excuse me,
excuse me, you've got a שביעית *Shvi'is* carrot excuse me you've got
a שביעית *Shvi'is* carrot and you've got תרומה *terumah* oil. Which one
when you cook them together, which one I think... No, ירק של
שביעית *yerek shel
Shvi'is*.
Okay. You've got a שביעית *Shvi'is* vegetable no he's going to say
what the opposite would have been but let's say what it is.
You have a שביעית *Shvi'is* carrot and תרומה *terumah* oil. Now if
you cook them together which one are you limiting? Which one are
you compromising? שביעית *Shvi'is* carrot, תרומה *terumah* oil. Which one is being
compromised? Which one is being limited the time it can be eaten
because you cook them together? The oil. The oil because of the
שביעית *Shvi'is* carrot. carrot, now this oil can be eaten for less
time. Give a banana שביעית! No, he's eating with the pure people.
Quiet. We're not worried about that right now. Okay, anyway, the תרומה
oil is biblical, okay? Oil on תרומה, it actually says explicitly דגן
תירוש ויצהר, Dagan Tirosh V'Yitzhar, okay? So the תרומה oil is biblical.
So when did רבה say, oh, we can limit the time of
things that are only rabbinic sanctity? Fine, but here it's true that
the שביעית carrot is rabbinic, but what you're doing is you're limiting
something with biblical sanctity because you're limiting the תרומה oil. So you
should have proven him from this case. Don't tell me he would
have dismissed it because it's rabbinic. What you can dismiss because it's
rabbinic is when the sanctity that's being constricted is rabbinic. But here
the sanctity is the שביעית—is the תרומה oil, and that's being constricted,
and even so רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon allows it. Okay, so he
says back to me, הכי one minute, if you wanted to say
this isn't relevant because it's rabbinic, איפכא מיבעי ליה למתני. Ipcha mibaei
lei l'misnei. Then it should have been the reverse, ירק של תרומה
בשמן של שביעית, Yerek shel Truma b'shemen shel Shviis, okay? Then it
should have said oh, you can cook a תרומה vegetable with שביעית
oil. Then you could have said oh, that doesn't prove anything because
the קדושה Kedusha. that's being restricted is only a rabbinic קדושה. Kedusha
But now that the oil is תרומה and the carrot is שביעית,
this is a good proof
against him because רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is לכתחילה lechatchila. letting you
limit the קדושה Kedusha of the תרומה, of the biblical קדושה of
the תרומה in the oil by cooking it together with the carrot.
So why didn't you ask him from this case? This is a
great case that you're allowed to do it לכתחילה. lechatchila. Everybody get
that? Okay, so you should have asked him. Here you see רבי
שמעון Rebbi Shimon, allows it לכתחילה lechatchila even with תרומה oil which
is biblical, which is דאורייתא. So אביי is going to say here's
why I didn't ask him that case.
So
ומי לא יוספיתיה ממתניתין U'mi lo yosfitey mi-masnisin דמטה רבי שמעון? d'matei
Rabbi Shimon? No, here's why I didn't ask him from the case
of the carrot and the oil, because I had already challenged him
from the משנה where the קרבנות get mixed up and רבי שמעון
Rebbi Shimon allows it. ואמר לי, V'amar li, and he answered me
back, דיעבד. No, no, no, that's דיעבד because the stuff's already mixed.
So therefore he told me—he wasn't impressed by a scenario—you mean you
asked him outside of this? Yeah, that was the first question was
from our משנה and he said דיעבד right after the—okay, and so—so
he said, "Yeah, yeah, yeah, once it's already mixed and there's a
problem, you've got to fix it. Then רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon will
allow it." So he would have said the same thing to me
about the carrot and the oil. Why? Because although our משנה makes
it sound like you're לכתחילה lechatchila putting your carrot in your frying
pan of oil, he would have said to me, "No, no, that
case that רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon allows you to cook the carrot
and oil together is that the carrot's already been soaking in the
oil and it's already after the fact, okay?" So that's not פשט
Pshat of the משנה, but that's what he would have said. הכי
נמי דיעבד. Hachi nami d'ieved. So you're asking me, רב יוסף, Rav
Yosef why didn't I challenge him from the משנה of the carrot
and the oil? Because he would have said to me, "That doesn't
mean לכתחילה lechatchila. you can fry your carrot in oil. That means
if your carrot has been soaking in oil, you can go ahead
and put it into the pot and into the pan. All right,
got it?" So okay, so רב יוסף says no, you can't say
that. אי דיעבד, Ei d'ieved, if the case there was that the
carrot was soaking in oil, מה טעמייהו דרבנן? Ma tamaihu d'Rabanan? Why—how
would the Rabbis say you're not allowed to cook it? What should
you do with it? Throw it out? Right, if it's already been
soaking in oil, of course you're allowed to cook it. What—what other
choice do you have? So the גמרא Gemara says so he
has מידי דהוה אאשם ושלמים. Midi dehavai a'asham ushlamim. So אביי said
back to him, "Well, what do you mean? The Rabbis disagreed with
him by the case of the animals, the אשם asham? and the
שלמים. shelamim. Of course there's an answer. There there's a fix. מי
דמי התם אית ליה תקנתא. Mi dami? Hasam is lei takanta. By
the אשם asham. and שלמים shelamim, there's a way to fix it.
ברעייה, Beria, you let them graze and you redeem them. הכא לית
ליה תקנתא ברעייה. Hacha leis lei takanta beria. What are you going
to do? Let your carrot graze? Okay, so anyway, all right, so
it's fascinating. Like you could have asked him this case, but again
to step back because you maybe got a little bit mixed in
the back and forth. Okay, can we prove that רבי שמעון Rebbi
Shimon allows it לכתחילה? lechatchila. So רב יוסף said you should have
proven it to him that רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon allows you to
cook the carrot and the oil לכתחילה together. And אביי said back,
"Nah, he just would have said that the carrot was already soaking
in oil and it's not a לכתחילה." So then to which the
response is that can't be because then why would the Rabbis argue?
And don't tell me the Rabbis argue in the משנה. There there's
an alternative. Here there's not an alternative. What are you supposed to
do with an—a carrot soaking in oil? Can you use it like
compost or—?
But it doesn't matter. The time period has already been limited because
it's soaking together. So what do you lose by cooking them together?
So if the case was that they were already soaking together, there
would be no logic to prohibit somebody from cooking it together. What
would be the alternative? So אביי is going to say wait, I
have a possible alternative. So the גמרא Gemara or רבינא Ravina is
going to say it. הלא דמיא לחתיכה שבחתיכות. Ha lo damya l'chaticha
she'b'chatichos.
What this case would be like is if you actually got the
meat of an אשם asham and שלמים shelamim, mixed up. And if
you have no solution, of course you're going to just treat it
like eat it like an אשם. asham So here too, the carrot
and the oil are mixed up, why should anybody why why would
if that were the case, how could the rabbis say don't cook
it together? What else are you supposed to do? Okay, so מתקיף
ליה רבינא, Matkif leh Ravina, so רבינא's Ravina got a solution. No,
it could be it was already soaking in oil and the rabbis
didn't want you to cook it because they thought that there was
a way you could salvage you could salvage the oil. What could
you do? מי דמי חתיכה שבתוכות ליתא תקנתא כלל. Mi dami chaticha
shebetochot leisa takanta klal. Meat of sacrifices that get mixed up,
there's literally nothing you can do. האי איתא תקנתא בסחיטה. Hai isat
takanta b'schita.
Here you can take the carrot and squeeze out the oil. Now,
not really, you're not going to get all the oil out, but
maybe the point is well at least the oil you do get
out, you'll salvage. Okay, of course the funny thing is, we're not
afraid that after it's been soaking together, the oil that comes out,
we're not concerned that it's got some taste of carrot in it
and that should limit it. That's a whole fascinating טעם taam question.
Okay, but he says maybe that's still the scenario, it's already mixed
together, and therefore for רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon it is a בדיעבד,
bediavad, and the only reason the rabbis don't agree is they feel
that you can salvage the oil, you can squeeze it out. So
the גמרא's Gemara going to respond back. רב יוסף, רב יוסף felt
give me a break. היכי נסחוט? Heichi nischot? How do you want
to squeeze it out? נסחוט טובא, Nischot tuva, really squeeze it out,
put it in one of those juice squeezers and get it all
out. So קא מפסיד בשביעית, Ka mafsid b'shvi'is, you're going to destroy
the carrot, which is שביעית. Okay, so that's not a solution. Okay,
נסחוט פורצא, Nischot portza, do a simple a simple squeeze. סוף סוף
מעורב. Sof sof me'orev. So there's still going to be oil left
in the carrot. Okay, so that's the carrot and the oil where
רב יוסף says if you want to prove that רבי שמעון Rebbi
Shimon allows it לכתחילה, yes, in the end you did prove it
from this case about
buying שביעית with מעשר money. Okay, but you could also have proved
it from the case of the carrot and the oil where clearly
that's a לכתחילה case. Don't tell me it's some בדיעבד bediavad case
it's already mixed together, and therefore even so רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon
allows it. So that is another example of רבי שמעון allowing it
לכתחילה. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara continues. איתיבי. Eiseivei. I'm going to
challenge you on this claim that רבי שמעון allows it לכתחילה. רבי
שמעון אומר: Rabbi Shimon omer: למחר מביא אשמו ולוגו. Lemachar meivi ashamo
v'lugo.
So you have a guy and that's what this תוספות Tosafos is
figuring out the exact scenario, who might be a מצורע metzora that
is a מצורע מוחלט, metzora muchlat, like a definite מצורע metzora that
basically he's been declared a full מצורע metzora and he, in order
to become טהור, tahor, needs to have the whole process with the
birds on day seven, and then bring a sacrifice on day eight.
But there's some doubt and he might not be a מצורע. metzora.
It's fascinating like since you need a כהן kohen to declare somebody
a מצורע, metzora, how do you have a doubt? But anyway, like
if he didn't declare him, he wasn't a מצורע. metzora. But anyway,
he might not be a מצורע metzora and therefore, how do you
bring the sacrifice on day eight to allow him to continue now
to be considered totally טהור tahor if he might not be obligated
in the sacrifice? So you make a lot of stipulations, okay? And
here's what you do. The day after his seven days, מביא אשמו
ולוגו. meivi ashamo v'lugo. You bring the אשם, asham which is a
male sacrifice, and the לוג log of oil, because remember you do
a whole ritual, the כהן kohen pours the oil on the hand,
he sprinkles it towards the קודש, kodesh, he puts some on the
ear and whatever. And then he pours from the hand on the
head. You got a whole ritual going on with the oil. Okay,
and so you bring the oil. ואומר, V'omer, and here's how you
stipulate: אם שמא מצורע, Im shema metzora, if this guy is a
real מצורע, metzora, הרי זה אשמו וזה לוגו. harei ze ashamo v'ze
lugo. So then it's like it looked like, this is the אשם
asham and this is the לוג שמן log shemen and we'll do
it as we're supposed to do it.
ואם לאו, V'im lav, אשמו זה שלמי נדבה. ashamo ze shalmei nedava.
This
אשם, asham we'll use we'll make it into a שלמים. shelamim. Okay,
ואותו אשם. v'oso asham. Now, what do you do with this אשם?
asham It might be a
שלמים shelamim and it might be an
אשם. asham. Now first of all let's say why did you make
it a שלמים? shelamim Why didn't you say an אשם asham, is
male, why didn't you say if it's not an אשם asham it'll
be an עולה? olah? Why do you think? You couldn't say if
it's not an אשם asham it'll be a חטאת, first of all
a חטאת is female. Second of all, a חטאת you only bring
if you have a sin. But why didn't you say if it's
not an אשם asham, let it be an עולה? olah? So just
think, what would you have to do with it if it were
an עולה? You'd have to burn it. You don't want to be
burning the meat that should be eaten. So you're going to say
if it's not אשם asham, it's a שלמים. shelamim Okay, now, a
שלמים Shlamim. could be eaten out of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
by anyone, an אשם asham. only by male כהנים. kohanim So it's
just like our משנה. There's a way though that we can get
all the meat eaten if you're going to be eating it by
male כהנים in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, okay? So ואם לאו,
v'im lav,
okay, ואותו אשם טעון שחיטה בצפון, v'oso asham taun shchita b'tzafon, slaughter
it in the north in case it's an אשם. asham. It might
be a שלמים but no harm, no foul. ומתן... U'matan... בהונות, bahonos,
you're going to put the blood on the guy's ears, which is
what you have to do if it's an אשם, asham, and if
it's a שלמים again, no harm no foul. וסמיכה, usemicha, you do
סמיכה semicha on it, which is what you're required to do by
a שלמים. תוספות Tosafot actually has a discussion, it could be that
by an אשם asham you're also required to do סמיכה semicha but
maybe only דרבנן סמיכה, semicha, okay, so סמיכה's semicha interesting. ונסכים, unesachim,
you bring the wine and the flour and the oil, which you
would bring if it were a שלמים, okay, ותנופת חזה ושוק, utnuvas
chaze veshok, and wave the חזה ושוק. chaze veshok. So waving the
חזה ושוק, chaze veshok, if it's an אשם asham, and you decided
to wave some meat over your head or whatever, be my guest,
okay, you want to play hopscotch with it, whatever, okay, fine. All
right, ונאכל ליום ולילה, vene'echal leyom valaylah, and you eat it for
a day and a night. So the part of and now the
real the real חידוש chiddush, here is also that the נסכים, nesachim,
but what an or if it's the real חידוש, chiddush but if
what you would do is you'd also stipulate and you say if
this is a שלמים, these are the נסכים, nesachim, if this is
an אשם, asham, then I'm bringing the נסכים nesachim as an independent
קרבן. korban, So one way or another you cover all your bases.
Anyway, why is this an איתיביה? iseivei? It's an איתיביה iseivei because
here רבי שמעון, it's an איתיביה iseivei to the claim, it's another
challenge to רבא. Rava, I think I said it wrong the first
time, it's not a question on, but whatever, it's another challenge to
רבא. Rava רבא, Rava you're saying that רבי שמעון only allows it
בדיעבד. bedi'eved. Here רבי שמעון is allowing you because you're eating this
stuff which might be an אשם, Asham you're also bringing it as
a שלמים. If it's a שלמים though you're limiting the time it
can be eaten, right, because you're treating it as an אשם. So
you רבא Rava, said that רבי שמעון only allows it בדיעבד. bedi'eved.
Here רבי שמעון is allowing you לכתחילה to bring a קרבן, korban
right, to bring to bring something that could be a שלמים and
to limit it like an אשם. Okay, now the answer to this
is obvious. This is not a לכתחילה case. There's a guy here
that's got to get טהור, tahor, right? So the answer is תיקוני
גברא שאני. tikunei gavra shani. No, come on, it's not a בדיעבד
bedi'eved in the sense that the stuff already is mixed up, like
the קרבן korban isn't in a problematic situation,
okay, that you're right about. But the man is in a problematic
situation, okay? So again, רבא Rava would say I can see that
רבי שמעון allows you to do it when the circumstances sort of
push you in that direction, okay? So you might not need the
קרבן korban, to be mixed up, here the guy is in a
problematic situation, but this does not prove to me, says רבא, that
רבי שמעון would allow it totally לכתחילה. All right, you got it?
Okay, so now we're going to say, okay, now let's figure out
how you're able to bring all this stuff. Let's bracket this קדשים
לבית הפסול for a minute, okay, we've sort of answered it. רבא
wants to insist that רבי שמעון only allows it בדיעבד, bedi'eved, but
there's a lot of very good evidence that רבי שמעון allows it
לכתחילה. He's completely unconcerned with it. Now we're going to just try
to figure out this case of the אשם, okay, independent of the
earlier discussion, this אשם that might be a שלמים that you're bringing
for this מצורע metzora guy, all right? So here's the case. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this:
התינח אשם. hasenach asham. I got how you do the אשם, you
make the stipulations, you wave it, the נסכים nesachim you bring you
make a stipulation about the נסכים. nesachim. לוג מאי איכא למימר? log
mai ika lemeimar? What about the oil? How do you play out
this oil thing, okay? Because in order to use the oil for
the אשם, for the מצורע, metzora, you have to sanctify it. Now
what do you do with the oil after you do the ritual
of the oil? The כהנים eat it and it actually has like
sanctity like a קרבן, korban okay. All right, that'll work if the
guy is a מצורע. metzora. Let's say the guy isn't a מצורע.
metzora. So what are you supposed to do with it? Now don't
say, now you could say maybe sanctify it בתנאי. bitnai. If this
guy's a מצורע metzora I'm sanctifying it, if not I'm not sanctifying
it and we're just bringing it to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
and going to do some some ritual with it. All right, what
would be the problem of doing that? Sanctifying it on a condition.
If the guy's a מצורע metzora it's sanctified, this oil, and we're
going to go through these rituals, and if he's not a מצורע
metzora then it's just unsanctified oil. Why do you think that would
be a problem? Any guesses?
Can you bring unsanctified oil to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and
do some some ritual with it? No, that's a problem of חולין
בעזרה. chulin ba'azarah. Okay, it's not just that physically the oil is
there, the oil is there and it's being used in this sort
of קרבן-like korban. ritual. So you can't not say that if it's
not being used for a מצורע metzora it's going to be unsanctified.
So what you have to say is if it's not going to
be used for a מצורע metzora I'm bringing it as its own
קרבן. korban, Now there's actually a הלכה, halacha now you might not
know this by reading the תורה, Torah, but the חז"ל Chazal say
you can just bring oil as a קרבן, korban and what you
would do is you would sort of treat it like a מנחה.
mincha. You would take a handbreadth of oil and put it on
the fire, I don't know how you'd get it all out off
of your hand, okay, and then you know the כהנים would eat
the rest, okay? So that's what you do. If this is for
the מצורע metzora ritual we'll do it that way, if it's not
then we're going to bring it as a קרבן korban and either
way the כהנים are going to eat what's left over. It's קדשים.
It's קדשים. Okay, but now the גמרא Gemara says wait wait, let's
figure out how this is going to play out, okay? So it
says like this: לוג
מאי איכא למימר. log mai ika lemeimar. So how do you how
do you sort of stipulate with
the
לוג? log? But wait a minute, but if the guy isn't a
מצורע, metzora, then you can't just go ahead and eat the oil.
You've got to do the קמיצה kmitzah and put some of the
oil on the fire. The גמרא Gemara says okay, תרתי עביד, tartei
avid, that is what you do. You both do the sprinkling and
the ritual of the מצורע metzora with the oil and you put
some of the oil on the fire and you eat the rest.
Wait, one minute, ודילמא מצורע הוא, vedilma metzora hu, maybe the guy
is a מצורע metzora ובעי מתן שבע? uvayei matan sheva? So the
גמרא Gemara is assuming that if you're putting it on the fire,
you're not doing the ritual. So the גמרא Gemara is saying wait,
but you've got to do the ritual. Fine, דעביד, de-avid, okay, fine,
you're doing both. You're doing some of the oil you're burning on
the fire and some of the oil you're using for the ritual
for the מצורע. metzora. והחסר ליה, ve-he-hasar lei, one minute. So the
גמרא Gemara assumes that what you're going to do is that, and
it's a question exactly a question why the גמרא Gemara assumes that
this is the order, hold on, let me just double check רש"י.
Rashi.
Right, the גמרא's Gemara going to assume that you're going to first
do the handbreadth and burn that on the fire before you do
the ritual of the sprinkling. Now, why exactly the גמרא Gemara assumes
that you have to do that order and not the opposite order
is not clear, but let's just work with that. It assumes that
first you do the handbreadth and then you're going to do the
sprinkling. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, if you did the
handbreadth first, you're not going to have the full amount of oil,
okay, and you need the full לוג log of oil to do
the ritual. Okay, I don't know why you can't start with more
than a לוג, log, but whatever. והחסר ליה, ve-he-hasar lei, but now
if you're doing the קמיצה kmitzah first, you're not going to have
the full לוג log of oil. So the גמרא Gemara says דמייתי
פוסתא ומלי ליה, demaiti pusta umali lei, you refill it, you're allowed
to refill. You bring a לוג log of oil, if something happens
to some of it, you're allowed to refill. דתנן, detnan, we learned
in the משנה: חסר הלוג עד שלא יצק, hasar halog ad shelo
yatzak, if the לוג log got something spilled out before the כהן
Kohen poured it onto his hand, okay, and started the ritual, ימלאנו,
yimalenu, refill it. So, you take a קמיצה, kmitzah, you burn it.
Now, maybe somehow you're allowed to do that, presumably the גמרא Gemara
assumes that that's the order, because presumably if you would start to
do the ritual of the sprinkling and it would already get like
sanctified that way, then maybe there'd be a problem with taking some
of that oil and burning it. Was it in a container or
something like that? Yeah, yeah, you go ahead, you bring it in
a bottle.
Here's your bottle of oil, okay. Sanctified it. What? Sanctified the oil.
But what do you sanctify it for?
You make a stipulation, you stipulate. If this guy's a מצורע, metzora,
it's sanctified as מצורע metzora oil, and if it isn't, it's sanctified
as a freewill offering, okay, and you stipulate the same way you
stipulate by the animal, as an אשם or שלמים. And you actually
bring extra oil when you do this originally so that you can
refill. Yeah, that you sanctified, the extra oil, you sanctified the extra
oil as well, yeah. Okay, so presumably, okay, so here's the guy,
here's that's the oil, here's the altar with the fire, okay, so
whatever, here's the fire, okay. So presumably if you were to do
the order first, if you first were to do it on him,
okay, and then would fully like sanctify it as מצורע metzora oil,
okay, presumably the גמרא Gemara then understands that then there would be
a problem taking the oil that's the remainder of it and putting
it on the fire. It's not clear why, but anyway, the גמרא
Gemara understands that the order first has to be, number one has
to be, we put some of it on the fire. That's number
one in case it's a נדבה. nedavah. And you haven't yet used
it here, so it's like you're more in a space where you
can possibly use it for something else, okay. Step number two is
that you're going to refill,
refill it. Now, step number three is you're going to now sprinkle
it on the guy, okay, whatever, and sprinkle it towards the
ארון, Aron, you also have a couple of sprinklings and then you
pour it on the head of the guy. Okay, so you take
care of that ritual, okay. So that's what you do: some on
the fire in case it's a נדבה, nedavah, refill it, sprinkle, and
so on. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says, והבעי הקטרה, vehabei
haktarah,
one minute, because I actually jumped ahead. Before I assumed that when
it said you took the קמיצה, kmitzah, you burned it. The גמרא
Gemara hasn't yet said you burned it. The גמרא Gemara really has
just step one as the כהן's Kohen got it in his hand,
okay, I don't know, that's a funny looking hand, but anyway, the
כהן Kohen has... whatever, you got the idea. Here's the כהן Kohen
and he's got oil in his hand, he's got oily hands. Okay,
so anyway, so you did the קמיצה, kmitzah, okay. So now the
גמרא Gemara says, okay, but you've got to burn that, alright. So
the גמרא says, והבעי הקטרה, vehabei haktarah, you've got to burn that
oil. דאקטר ליה, de-aktar lei, fine, you'll burn it. אימת, eimat, now
when are you going to burn it? אי בתר מתנות שבע, ei
batar matnot sheva, if you're going to burn it after you do
the sprinkling on this guy and the sprinkling towards the ארון Aron
and whatever, if this is going to be step number four, so
then we've got a problem. What problem do we have? הוו להו
שיריים שחסרו בין קמיצה להקטרה ואין מקטירין את הקומץ עליהם. havu lei
shiyarei shechasru bein kmitzatah l'haktarah v'ein maktirin et hakometz aleihem. Okay,
so the הלכה is, you take let's assume like a מנחה. mincha.
You take your קמיצה kmitzah and you're going to walk it over
and burn it on the altar, okay? Before you get to there,
some of the מנחה mincha spills. All right, you are not allowed
to burn the קמיצה kmitzah if the remnant, the שיריים shiyarayim that
you left behind afterwards is not the complete amount. All right, so
that's a general principle. So here, if you took the קמיצה kmitzah
and then sprinkled it, this is going to be offered up on
remnant that has not is not the complete amount. And you're not
allowed to burn this if this isn't complete. So you can't introduce
the sprinkling between the קמיצה kmitzah and the burning. Can't do anything
between that. The קמיצה kmitzah and the burning. Right. So the גמרא
says, right. So אי בתר מתנות שבע, ee batar matnot sheva, if
you do קמיצה, kmitzah, then you do the sprinkling and then you're
going to burn it, שיריים שחסרו בין קמיצה להקטרה, shiyarayim shechasru bein
kmitzah l'haktarah,
the remnant, some of it got lost between the קמיצה kmitzah and
the burning. ואין מקטירין את הקומץ עליהם, v'ein maktirin et hakometz aleihem,
and you can't then burn the קומץ kometz on שיריים shiyarayim that
is not complete. So the גמרא says: אי קודם מתנות שבע, ee
kodem matnot sheva, fine,
let's say you go ahead and you do it like we thought.
You take the קמיצה, kmitzah, you burn it, and then you get
around and doing the sprinkling. That makes sense, just get through with
it and then move on to the next step. Okay. כל שממנו
לאישים הרי הוא בבל תקטירו. koshe mimenu l'ishim harei hu b'val taktiru.
No,
because anything that was used in a sacrificial context you cannot burn
on the altar. So like, huh? What? What does this mean? So
רש"י Rashi says what it means is the following. רש"י Rashi says
and this is a fascinating idea. Okay, there's a pr- there's a
principle which is, which is, you know, לא תקטירו ממנו אשה להשם.
lo saktiru mimenu isheh l'Hashem. Okay, that you know,
something that was used already as a קרבן korban can't be offered
up and burned on the altar. So like let's say for example,
a simple example because this is similar to a מנחה. mincha. You
burnt the קמיצה kmitzah on the מנחה, mincha, I'm now going to
go ahead and take the remnant of this מנחה mincha and burn
it on the fire, on the altar fire as if it's an
offering. That would be a violation. Anything that was sort of already
used in a sacrificial context but is not itself put on the
altar, you cannot, you know, כל שממנו לאישים, kol shemimenu l'ishim, anything
that a part of it went on the fire, so think about
a מנחה, mincha, some of the מנחה mincha went on the fire,
the remnant of it cannot be הרי זה בבל תקטירו, harei zeh
b'val taktiru, the remnant of it cannot be burned on the fire.
Now, what here is being burned on a fire? So the way
רש"י Rashi reads this is fascinating. You went ahead and you did
your קמיצה kmitzah and you burnt it. That, this is ממנו לאישים.
mimenu l'ishim. The remnant of the oil, some of it went to
the fire. Now and because it might all be נדבה nedava oil.
You're now going to use it as a ritual on this מצורע
metzora towards the- towards the קודש, kodesh, רש"י Rashi says the same
way you're not allowed to use this remnant of the oil and
burn it on the fire, לא תקטירו, lo saktiru, you can't use
the remnant of the oil and use it in some מקדש mikdash
ritual. That- sprinkling it on the guy, sprinkling it towards the- towards
the קודש, kodesh, רש"י Rashi says that is like an act of
הקטרה. haktarah. So that's a big חידוש because the verse emphasizes לא
תקטירו. lo saktiru. But for רש"י Rashi that's the problem. Once you
put some of this on the fire, this remnant, the same way
you're not allowed to burn this remnant on the fire, you're not
allowed to use this remnant in this ritual. Okay, that's the way
רש"י Rashi reads it. תוספות Tosafot reads it in a different way,
but let's go with רש"י Rashi then I'll go back and tell
you how תוספות Tosafot reads it. And she said because I mean
I'm just reading the note, because it's corresponding to the burning of
animal sacrifices on the altar, that sprinkling is the same as burning.
That's what I'm saying. The sprinkling on this, the sprinkling on the
מצורע metzora or the sprinkling towards the ארון aron is similar to
burning a קרבן korban on the fire, right. Okay, I don't know
if you need to say animal, but it's similar to burning a
קרבן korban on the fire. Yeah, yeah, yeah. Okay, so that's what
רש"י Rashi says. The same way I can't take the remnant of
this oil and burn it on the fire, I can't take the
remnant of this oil and use it in that in some type
of a מקדש mikdash ritual. Okay, that's how רש"י Rashi says. But
how are you sure you would need the remnant because there's not
going to be enough? Is that... not that there's not going to
be enough, it's just a prohibition. כל שממנו לאישים, kol shemimenu l'ishim,
if some of a קרבן korban. went on the fire, the stuff
that didn't go on a fire you're not allowed to offer on
the fire. הרי זה בבל תקטירו. harei zeh b'val taktiru. And רש"י
Rashi is saying בל תקטירו bal taktiru to read this גמרא doesn't
just mean you can't put it on the fire, but you can't
use it in some other מקדש mikdash ritual. Okay? So that... he
equates like when this fellow is getting his... being sprinkled, he's like
a... he's feeling as if it's some kind of... something is being
offered on him or something like that. Yeah, I know, I do
think that that is powerful, right. That saying that the sprinkling on
him or the spr- it's not exactly only the sprinkling on him
or the sprinkling towards the מקדש, mikdash, but one of the ways
we're seeing that is actually a type of a קרבן. korban, Right,
that's clearly how רש"י Rashi is looking at it. Okay. So how
you going to do this? How can you now use this for
the ritual?
אמר רבי יהודה בריה דרבי שמעון. amar Rabi Yehuda brei d'Rabi Shimon.
Nah, you just treat it like wood. Okay, what does that mean?
דתניא, detanya, רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, לריח ניחוח אי אתה
מעלה, l'reiach nichoach ee atta ma'aleh, you can't burn certain things on
the altar doing them as a type of a קרבן, korban, אבל
אתה מעלה לשם עצים, aval atta ma'aleh l'shem eitzim, you can say
it's just fuel, I'm just putting it on the fire not as
a קרבן, korban, as fuel. So when you have these types of
cases where, one minute, if this is not the right thing, you're
not allowed to burn it, then what you say is, fine, if
it's not the right thing, I'm not putting it on the fire
as a קרבן, korban, I'm just putting it on the fire to
feed the fire, it's fuel. So now the funny thing here is
we're not feeding a fire the way רש"י Rashi is reading it.
What רש"י Rashi really says the גמרא wanted to say is after
I go ahead and put this on the fire, I can't use
this remnant for a ritual. So what I'm going to say is
the following. If this guy is a מצורע metzora and this is
מצורע metzora oil, I'm doing this as מצורע metzora sprinkling. If this
guy isn't a מצורע metzora and I've already brought part of this
as a קרבן, korban I'm just doing this to cool him off.
I'm not doing this as a ritual, I'm just doing this like
water. Okay, and therefore you can sort of pretend and you're not
really doing it. The same way you could burn stuff on the
fire as fuel and it wouldn't be a violation, you could just
do that for fun. Okay, we're just playing a game. Okay, so
that's the way רש"י Rashi reads it. What bothers תוספות Tosafot is
that when it says you treat it like wood, clearly means we're
talking about something you're putting on a fire. The way רש"י Rashi
should have said it and the way the גמרא says it in
other contexts is you should just say if it's not real then
it's just like water. You shouldn't have said it's just like wood,
you should have said it's just like water, which is what the
גמרא says in other contexts. So that's תוספות's Tosafot question on רש"י,
Rashi, which leads to the way תוספות Tosafot reads it, and let
me just double check before I say it. Okay, so תוספות Tosafot
says like this, hold on,
I'm just going to double check the way תוספות Tosafot reads
it. Right, so תוספות Tosafot says like this. תוספות Tosafot says the
problem is not the sprinkling. תוספות Tosafot said the problem is like
this. The same way you're not allowed to take the remnant of
a מנחה mincha and burn it up on the altar, ממנו לאישים
mimenu l'eishim you're not allowed to burn up, he says in the
scenario that this oil is מצורע metzora oil, he says now this
is either one of two ways you have to bridge a gap.
רש"י Rashi said sprinkling is like burning up. תוספות Tosafot says no
no no, we're talking about really burning. What we're asking is how
are you allowed to burn this? And now, why not? Because the
same way you're not allowed to burn let's say the remnant of
a מנחה, mincha, if this is מצורע metzora oil, so that's being
used in a particular ritual, that's sanctified for a particular ritual, you're
not allowed to burn something that has another קרבן korban role. The
same way you can't burn the remnant of a מנחה mincha because
it's got another קרבן korban role and you're not allowed to burn
it on the altar, this which has a קרבן role of oil
used for מצורע, metzora, how are you allowed to burn מצורע metzora
oil on the altar? You can't burn leftover מנחה mincha on the
altar, how are you allowed to burn מצורע metzora oil on the
altar? Okay? And the answer is, it's just fuel. The same answer
you treat it like fuel. So רש"י Rashi says the question is
how are you allowed to sprinkle נדבה nedavah oil on the מצורע,
metzora, and the answer is you pretend that it's just water. תוספות's
Tosafot question is how are you allowed to burn מצורע metzora oil
on the altar? And the answer is you treat it just like
it's fuel. So one way or the other you sort of pretend
and you're able to sort of do it both ways. Okay, okay,
so now we'll end with that for now. We're already one full
דף ahead from the normal דף and to be continued tomorrow.